Welcome back, excited to have you here.
And today we're gonna
cover database principles
and this is foundation knowledge
that is critically important
to everything you learn in
SQL Server from here on out.
We have a unique approach today.
After you finish this
particular video, you'll
be able to take the
module one activity quiz
and then homework number
one and hopefully you've
got the syllabus review
quiz done and then read
chapter three or the
topics for chapter three.
The class approach for
today is interesting.
It follows a gentleman
named David Ossible.
Dr. Ossible was a famous
psychologist and came up with
a number of theories,
including advanced organizers.
The idea of an advanced organizers
is to relate what a student
already knows to new content being
learned. And this particular lesson
fits perfectly with that. Dr. Osible
had a very famous instructional
design student, M. David Merrill.
M. David Merrill taught at USU
Stanford, also at Utah State, and
he had a graduate student, me.
I pretty much teach in the basement
of the business building, and
then you. So here is the approach.
We do this workshop, but because
it's online, I've had my wife, Kim,
who is going through this guessing
game trying to tie existing
knowledge and the new knowledge that
we'll talk about so Kim is just
retired this year she is the former
teacher of the year for all 30
cash schools so the question is are
you smarter than and now it needs
to say a retired second grade
teacher but we'll use Kim as we go
through the terms and she'll try to
guess the term based on terms
that you're already familiar with,
and then I'll explain the concepts
briefly as we move through today.
So here we go with the first
clue. See if you can guess
the keyword that we'll cover
as I give clues to Mrs. Mills.
So you don't have a lot of
day-based background, correct?
No. All right. Here come the
first three clues. All right.
Coffee, top,
dinner.
You know the soft top.
Okay,
how about, the word was table.
Table.
Dinner table,
coffee table,
light or something.
Okay, so you don't have to.
All right, so the key
word there is table.
Earlier we talked about the idea of
a penny and how a penny can be fairly
difficult. but the penny also
represents one in a database and so
when you think about a tables in a
house you have a dinner table which is
usually used just for dinner ideally
and then you might have a coffee
table which is just for putting
drinks on and so in a database context
a table is no different the idea is
you have one theme per table so if
you're working with a small
organization and you have, for instance,
this spreadsheet here, you certainly
look at columns A, B, C, and it looks
like kind of a student theme or a
student table. And then from D on,
Locker, Locker Location Manager
Phone, that starts to look like kind
of something different, right?
Maybe the Arc has a Locker database.
And so in this particular
case, in a spreadsheet it might
be okay, but in database you
would have to break that apart.
And we will do that systematically
using normalization.
There are some other rules we'll
get into that are related to
normalization. It's also one
piece of information per cell.
So you can have one last name
and one first name and so forth.
One record,
excuse me, one row per record.
So if we take Mills here, Megan
Mills, she can only have row
three. She can't start hogging more
rows, as you sometimes would
do in a spreadsheet where you
might give somebody two rows to
have two different phone numbers,
and then one data type per
column. So if this is character,
they all have to be character.
If this is numeric, it should be
numeric. So it should be the
same data type for the column. So
that all represents the theme
of one as it relates to a table.
Here's an example of a relational
table that we just discussed. So
if we had that original spreadsheet
we normalize it and we would break
it into two different tables and
these tables have a relationship
with each other we'll cover this
more in about about a week or two
and when you do create a table
this is looking way forward and
this is one of the first test
questions that you have on your
exam how to create a table from
scratch that'll be one of your
requirements and this is somewhat
cryptic but you can read it
create a table, student, we've
got this parenthesis, this
looks like the column name,
these are the data types, this
is kind of strange, but it's
a surrogate key, we'll get to
that, and so that will be how
you will create these tables.
All right, next clue. Good
luck, Kim, let's do this.
All right, this one's in your wheelhouse.
Okay, but I'm gonna have trouble
with clues here. um vinyl
what does it start with r okay
vinyl vinyl yeah vinyl lp song
starts with an r oh yeah
vinyl lp record yeah
All right, so the next term is record.
In a database, we have rows and
columns and cells. The nice thing is
you're familiar with that if you're
familiar with the spreadsheet.
They do have different
names, though. You'll
see a row, a typical row in the data set.
A row represents...
Another name for a row is also a record.
This entire row consists of
a record. It's also called
a tuple. You can think of
tuple. It rhymes with couple.
And in the SQL industry, that's
what they refer to it as, a tuple.
A column is also considered
a field or an attribute. So
everything here should be related.
These should be all student
IDs, and these should all be
class IDs, and these should
all be grades. And then a cell
is simply an intersection of
a column and a row. So we do
have some different language.
Typically, the terms here
are used more when we're
designing the database, and
then the row, column, and
cell are used more when
we're using the data set.
All right, next clue.
Clues. I'm 0 for 1.
Car.
Unique.
House.
All right, so the term is key.
And when we refer to a
key in SQL, we'll refer to
a primary key. We also
refer to non-keys, and this
becomes important when
we're normalizing data.
We'll use the term non-key.
But a primary key, by definition,
is a column that uniquely
identifies a row. So if you
give me your social security
number, I can look and your
social security number should
uniquely identify you. Same
thing with an A number. If you
give me an A number, that will
automatically identify you.
It ideally should be numeric,
a number, non-repeating, obviously,
and have no meaning to the user.
So if you had to decide between a
social security and an A number,
you'd pick the A number because it
has less or no meaning to the user.
It also creates what's
called a cluster index.
And a clustered index and indexing
is beyond what we will cover
formally, but the term clustered
index simply means when you create a
primary key and you think about a
phone book, a phone book is indexed,
of course, in alphabetical order,
and so it creates that clustered
index based on your primary key and
what that does is it allows you to
quickly look up information because
it's clustered index it determines
how that data will physically
be stored in the in the database
itself and it makes it more efficient
because it's physically stored and
ordered you can only have one
clustered index allowed per table
because that's physically stored
a phone book you can't have it two
different ways If you think about
even a back of a book, too, might have
an index, and that index is generally
sorted by alphabetical order.
A primary key in a database diagram
is represented by the PK here. You
can see the PK, and then anything
else would be a non-key attribute.
And then to add a primary key,
again, this will be a couple weeks.
We're just looking forward,
but you can see this is how we
create a table. and then we need
a primary key. So looking ahead
we'll write the word constraint
student underscore PK which hence
this is the name of it and what
is it it'll be a primary key and
in parentheses this is the primary
key in this case student ID.
Good luck. This clue starts with an N.
It's four letters. four letters. Empty.
Zero.
Niche.
Absence.
Incomplete.
No.
No. I do know that.
That is fine. The one
value that I provided
just to bring up in this
conversation is zero.
And if you think about
it, zero is a number.
How many elective courses
have you taken? Zero.
That would be different than null.
Now null would suggest
that you don't know
or you haven't decided.
So a null value, not to
overcomplicate it, but
if you see a null value,
it is simply the absence of a
value. So it's either been undecided
or it's just not known. And the null
values have a lot of ramifications
as we code, so in some cases
we write code and it calculates
or includes null values. In other
cases it ignores null values, and
so as we go through we'll figure
that there are different times when
we want to include null values,
and there's also times when we
don't want to include null values.
If you think back to 2100, many
of you have forgotten this. I've
asked it in prior semesters, but
here we have select star from customer
where phone number, and typically
you see equal, right, or not
equal or some equality symbol. But
in this case, null value is
important enough that we say is null.
And the reason it's not equal to null
is because it's not equal to null.
It's an unknown, and that's why it
is null instead of equal to null.
this one starts with a c okay and wait
till i give you the
three clues okay romney
president obama okay
let me think of some
more selection chosen
um counted committee country candidate
this one starts with a c candidate
key candidate key and as we go
through these these are these are
such important terms to remember
long term think of i don't know
the b verbs when you were in
fourth grade, and we had a contest.
Who could say him the fastest?
Is, and, be, or was, were, been,
be, been, being, or something.
These terms are important to know
because the rest of the semester,
and really the rest of your career,
this is just common terminology. And
so when we talk about normalization,
if you understand these terms,
it will make all of the other learning
a little bit easier than having
to go back and figure out what these
terms mean. But Canada does fit.
If you think of Romney or Trump or
Obama, these were candidates and
only one would be selected as president.
So right now we have a President
Trump in office. And so a candidate
key is a column that could have
been president. So Harris could
have been president, but only one is
picked. And so as a database person,
you can choose among candidate
keys, which one will be the primary
key. and going back to a couple
slides ago the idea would be is it
numeric is it non-repeating does it
have no meaning to the user in this
particular case you could probably
use well you could use I think
locker number if those are unique and
then you have the serial number and
those are all unique too and then
I guess the lock or combo are probably
unique locations not unique so
in this case this is numeric non
-repeating no meaning to the user and
that would be the idea that I would
recommend for a candidate key and
also a candidate key is considered
this will be another term on the
midterm exam just saying a candidate
key is a minimal super key and a
super key is just a combination of
columns that can make a candidate
key and so in this case all you
need is this alone to determine the
candidate key that would be a super
key but another super key could be
location plus the locker and you
think well yes of course but that is
it's not minimal but it is a super
key and so every combination that
does create something that could
be used is considered a super key a
minimal one is when you is what we
typically look at this is a minimal
one that could be used by itself as
a super key i guess that means move
to the next slide I think we're
going forward let's see no friends
this one starts with an F okay
international foreign Wow so foreign and
we're talking about a foreign key
now remember earlier we talked about
this the themes one theme per table
so So we have a student theme and
we have a locker theme. So we need
to break those two tables apart.
But later, we have to be able to
put those tables back together. So
there's always one thing that doesn't
quite look like it perfectly fits.
So I always think of serial and
I drop something in my serial and
it doesn't look right. It's for
an object. And so in this case,
the requirement is when we have
two tables to link them together,
we have to take the primary key
from one table and put it into
the other. So in this case, it
looks like we have student ID,
last name, first name, and then
we have some locker information.
So student ID and locker number
are primary keys. We would
have to take one of those and
put it into the other table.
Now, in this case, we'll likely
take the student ID and put it in
the locker table because student
table is a little bit more
important probably than the locker
table. But in a couple of weeks,
we'll learn the formal process
for doing that based on the
relationship between those two tables.
and we'll talk about that later.
But the foreign key is always
the key that doesn't quite fit,
but it needs to be there to connect
these two tables together. We
don't have Kim on this one
because this is a tough one,
but if you think about metals, and
sometimes metals might have steel
and copper, and you put those
metals together, that's considered a
composite. So anytime you put two
or more things together, that's
composite. This is a picture of
the car that I had, my first car in
Hawaii going to school, and as you
can see on the top here there wasn't
a roof. It was all rusted out. So
we went down to, a friend and I
went down and we got bondo. And so
this bondo is two parts, so like
a pink and a white part, and we
mixed it together. And then what we
were able to do is kind of paint
a roof on. So bondo is a composite
material. What that means in the
database context, though, and think
about composite, it just means two
or more columns are combined to
make or uniquely identify a row or
to make a primary key. So if you
think about your grade, so you go
down to your advisor and you ask,
what's my grade? The first thing
they may ask is, who are you? Oh,
I'm student one. But then you
can take more than one class,
so they would have to know which
class. So to determine your
grade, you would have to have
a composite key. You You need
two pieces of information in
order to determine your grade.
And this word is unique, I
guess we don't have a video
for it, but unique is
referring to a surrogate key.
And a surrogate key is a numeric added
column that can serve as the primary key.
And so earlier I showed
you the create table and I
mentioned, I actually mentioned
this looks a little strange,
the identity one comma one.
And so in this case, identity
is the way that we'll use
to create a surrogate key.
So when you create a table, if you
write identity 1, 1, that means
we're going to start with these
numbers. It's going to start at 1, and
it's going to increment by 1. So
this would give you 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
On this customer number, same
thing. It's going to start at
1 and increment by 1. And if we
put 10 here, it would start at
10 and then increment by 1. Or
if we started at 1 and put a
5 there, it would start at 1
and then increment by 5. So it
would go 1 and 5, 1 and 6, and
then increase by 5 each time.
All right, this word starts with an I.
These are tough to find clues.
So moral, standard, personal.
Individual.
Personal,
moral,
standard.
Oh, someone's kind of like their compass.
Okay. Yeah.
Integrity. Integrity.
Correct.
I didn't do very well on those
clues, but the word is integrity. And
this is a great concept in databases
where we have something called
referential integrity. So when we
normalize the database in a week, the
idea is to make the data more reliable
and have less redundant data. And
having redundant data, you can have
errors and which error is correct
or which item is correct and which
is error if we have discrepancies.
So the idea of referential
integrity is to help maintain the
database where a primary key
must exist before you can
establish a foreign key. But
writing the constraint is indicating
where the foreign key is. And
so here is the idea of it.
Let's say you go over here to
this locker and now I want to
build a new locker and I tell
them that I am student ID 11.
And what it will do, and this is
the wording of it, it'll say student
ID and locker must exist in student
ID in the student table, and I
always remember this just because F
foreign comes before P primary, so
that's how I remember which table
comes first, but that's the formal
definition, so student ID in the
locker table must exist in student ID
in the student table, meaning you
can't add a locker unless you exist
as a student, so if I go to the ARC
and I'm like, hello, I'd like to,
you know, rent a locker, and they're
like, okay, what's your A number,
and I say, my A number is 11,
they're going, sorry, you're not a
student, you have to be a student
to be able to do that. So that helps
to protect the database. Otherwise,
if they allow me to do it, and
there's an emergency, and now they
have to look up an emergency contact,
there is no student 11,
so it doesn't exist. So
the database is protected
with this referential
integrity. And then the
last term for today is meta.
And meta technically means about.
So sometimes meta is
used in different ways.
You'll be watching the news, and
they'll say, you know, the government
is tracking our data. They're collecting
metadata. They have your phone
number. They have your phone calls.
They have your time of call. Well,
in a database context, that's all
data. And so metadata in our context
is data about the data. So if you
remember when we said create table,
that is metadata. That's how we're
creating the table. So the metadata
is data about the data.
And for now, if you
just think about when we
did that create table,
and these are the columns and these
are the data types we'll get to
later and this is if you can leave it
null or if it has to have information
and then this one here identity 1
comma 1 remember what that was that's
a surrogate key and is that the
primary key well it probably will be
but it's not until we do this
constraint and make it student ID the
primary key it becomes but this is
the data about the data it's not the
data itself so sometimes you look
at this and you think where am I or
where where is the student right this
is just a shell this is the structure
it takes a little while to understand
that because this is different
than a spreadsheet I think of
metadata there are two different types
this will be the last slide so there's
DDL which stands for data definition
language and I have on when we
create a table that's data definition
when we delete a table you get
rid of the whole table well that's
table level so that's a DDL test. Or
when you alter the table, you're going
to add a column or delete a column.
So all of that is considered data
definition language. Data manipulation
language is likely what you did
in 2100, where you might have just
questioned the database. How many
students participate in activities?
So you write your select statement.
Also, if you insert a row, that's
just one row, so that's data
manipulation, not the full
table. Or if you delete a row,
somebody leaves school, so you
delete that row or if you simply
update change somebody's name
all of those would be considered
dml tasks and again all through
the semester we'll talk ddl dml
and it will become very you know
very much conversational language
for you so this is an overview
of the database principles